<document>

<properties>
<author email="adammurdoch@apache.org">Adam Murdoch</author>
<title>User Guide</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Building Myrmidon">

<p>
First, you will need to fetch the Myrmidon source from CVS.  The source
can be source in the <code>proposal/myrmidon</code> directory of the
Ant source tree.  You should check out the <code>jakarta-ant</code> CVS
module, as described
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html">here</a>.
</p>

<p>
To build Myrmidon, use the <code>build.xml</code> build script.  You will need
to use Ant 1.4.1 or later.  The default target builds the Myrmidon distribution
into the <code>dist</code> directory.  The distribution is a ready-to-run
installation of Myrmidon.
</p>

<p>There are a number features that are not built unless the appropriate optional Jar
files are found in the <code>lib</code> directory:</p>

<table>
    <tr><th>Feature</th><th>Jar File</th><th>Download From</th></tr>
    <tr>
        <td>SMB VFS support (Samba, Windows shares)</td>
        <td>jcifs.jar</td>
        <td><a href="http://jcifs.samba.org">jcifs.samba.org</a>.
        <p>Note: there are problems using the 0.6.1 release.  Try 0.6.0 instead.</p></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>FTP VFS support</td>
        <td>netcomponents.jar</td>
        <td><a href="http://www.savarese.org/oro/software/NetComponents.html">www.savarese.org</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>

</section>

<section name="Running Myrmidon">

<p>
To run Myrmidon, use one of the following methods:
</p>

<subsection name="Launcher Script">

<p>
On Windows and Unix platforms, you can use the <code>ant</code> script
in the distribution's <code>bin</code> directory.  The following environment
variables can be used, but are not required (except on Windows 9x - see below).
</p>

<p>

</p>

<table>
    <tr><th>Variable</th><th>Description</th></tr>
    <tr>
        <td>JAVA_HOME</td>
        <td>The directory that the JDK is installed in.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>JAVACMD</td>
        <td>The command to use to start the JVM.  Defaults to <code>java</code>.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>ANT_HOME</td>
        <td>
            The directory containing the Myrmidon distribution.  This must be
            set when running on Windows 95, 98 or Me.
        </td>
    </tr>
</table>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Executable Jar File">

<p>
The Myrmidon distribution includes an executable Jar file, which can be used
to run Myrmidon.  Use the following command:
</p>
<pre>
prompt> <i>java</i> -jar <i>ant-home</i>/bin/myrmidon-launcher.jar <i>options</i>
</pre>

</subsection>

<p>When started, Myrmidon looks for a project file called <code>build.ant</code>
in the current directory.  A different project file can be specified using the
<code>-f</code> command-line option.  Myrmidon executes the targets given on
the command-line, or the default target if none is given.  For example, the
following executes the targets <code>clean</code> and <code>build</code> from
the project file <code>my-project.xml</code>:</p>

<pre>
prompt> ant -f my-project.xml clean build
</pre>

<p>
Run Myrmidon with the <code>-h</code> command-line option for a list of
the command-line options that are available.
</p>

</section>

</body>

</document>
