<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
    <title>Regexp</title>
  </properties>

<body>

  <section name="Regexp">

<p>
Regexp is a 100% Pure Java Regular Expression package that was graciously 
donated to the Apache Software Foundation by Jonathan Locke. He originally wrote 
this software back in 1996 and it has stood up quite well to the test of time. 
It includes complete Javadoc documentation as well as a simple Applet for visual 
debugging and testing suite for compatibility.
</p>

<p>
This package is intended to be an answer to a question we commonly hear in the 
Java world:
<br/>
<strong>&quot;Why isn't there a decent regular expression package available for 
Java under a BSD-Style (ie: Apache) license?&quot;</strong>
</p>

<p>
You can <a href="../site/binindex.html">download</a> builds.
</p>

<p>
You can view the list of 
<a href="./changes.html">changes</a> between revisions.
</p>

<p>
The Javadoc is <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/regexp/apidocs/">available online</a>. 
It is also included in the distribution download.
</p>

<p>
An online <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/jyve-faq/Turbine/screen/DisplayTopics/action/SetAll/project_id/2/faq_id/27">FAQ</a>
is available for commonly asked questions like, &quot;What is a regular
expression?&quot;, &quot;Why did you do this? There are already other Java
regexp packages available!&quot;, etc. 
</p>

<p>
If you would like to get involved with this project in one way or another 
(Mailing lists, CVS, Contributions), please see the <a 
href="../site/getinvolved.html">Getting Involved</a> section of the Jakarta Website.
</p>

<h3><a href="../site/whoweare.html">Contributors</a></h3>

<ul>
<li>Jonathan Locke wrote the original code.</li>
<li>James Davidson for making the contact with Jonathan and asking him to release his 
source code.</li>
<li>Jon S. Stevens is responsible for re-packaging it and preparing it 
for release.</li>
<li>Craig McClanahan is responsible for setting up the CVS and mailing lists.</li>
<li><a href="mailto:ales AT netbeans.com">Ales Novak</a> has contributed
bug fixes and feature enhancements.</li>
</ul>

  </section>

</body>
</document>

