<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Apache Ant Mission</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Board Resolution">
    
    <p>Apache Ant is a project of the <a
    href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.  It
    started as a subproject of the <a
    href="http://jakarta.apache.org/">Apache Jakarta Project</a>.</p>

    <p>This is the board resolution (from the <a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/records/minutes/2002/board_minutes_2002_11_18.txt">minutes</a>)
    that created the Apache Ant project:</p>

    <source>
7.D. Resolution [R3] to create the Ant PMC

WHEREAS, the Board of Directors deems it to be in the best
interests of the Foundation and consistent with the
Foundation's purpose to establish a Project Management
Committee charged with the creation and maintenance of
open-source software related to the Apache Ant build tool, for
distribution at no charge to the public.

NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED, that a Project Management
Committee (PMC), to be known as the "Apache Ant PMC", be and
hereby is established pursuant to Bylaws of the Foundation; and
be it further

RESOLVED, that the Apache Ant PMC be and hereby is responsible
for the creation and maintenance of the Ant build system and
related software components, based on software licensed to the
Foundation; and be it further

RESOLVED, that the office of "Vice President, Apache Ant" be
and hereby is created, the person holding such office to serve
at the direction of the Board of Directors as the chair of the
Apache Ant PMC, and to have primary responsibility for
management of the projects within the scope of responsibility
of the Apache Ant PMC; and be it further

RESOLVED, that the persons listed immediately below be and
hereby are appointed to serve as the initial members of the
Apache Ant PMC:

   Bruce Atherton
   Stephane Bailliez
   Stefan Bodewig
   Erik Hatcher
   Diane Holt
   Donald Leslie
   Steve Loughran
   Conor MacNeill
   Costin Manolache
   Sam Ruby
   Jon Skeet
   Magesh Umasankar
   Christoph Wilhelms

NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, that Conor MacNeill be
and hereby is appointed to the office of Vice President, Apache
Ant, to serve in accordance with and subject to the direction
of the Board of Directors and the Bylaws of the Foundation
until death, resignation, retirement, removal or
disqualification, or until a successor is appointed; and be it
further

RESOLVED, that the initial Apache Ant PMC be and hereby is
tasked with the creation of a set of bylaws intended to
encourage open development and increased participation in the
Apache Ant Project.

By Unanimous Vote, Resolution R3 was approved. The Ant PMC is
hereby created.
    </source>

  </section>
</body>
</document>